Okay. Hello again, cohort 8. It's March
20th and we're in
our first discussion on chapter 3.
Lots of ways to enter into this, but
just to start, would anyone like to
um point to a quote in three or a
figure or any area of three or how they
see chapter 3 in the context of the
book or how they see the low road and
the high road? Uh well, I have a
question about the sort of the end, I
guess.
um uh where it says I'll just read the
whole paragraph even though my question
might not really be about the whole
paragraph. Uh an active inference agent
appears to perform approximate basian
inference under a generative model to
maximize evidence for its model that is
a self-evident agent. The perspective
bit of inference is realized by
selecting courses of action or policies
that are expected to minimize free
energy f in the future. This formalism
leads to a novel view of optimal
behavior in terms of Hamiltonian
principle of lease action. Uh yeah, I
guess that's I guess my question is
about that sentence.
Um I'm not sure.
Uh yeah, I I guess I don't not sure I
believe that.
So there's a discrepancy in what you
observed and what you believed. And so
there's two ways to play that out. By
changing what you believe or by taking
some kind of action. Do you believe
that?
Um well maybe there might be more than
two in in uh but
um there might be those two. But uh so
one problem I see with this is I had I
had it highlighted.
Uh so it says it says something else.
Hold on. Uh let me try to find what I
was looking for.
But yeah, being a little clearer about
what what part you
Yeah. So the like there there's Yeah. So
that was at the end of the chapter to be
clear that what I just read was from the
very end of chapter three but there is
also a tiein
uh okay yeah so it gives three
associations
um between active inference and
Hamiltonian
dynamics. The first one is just you know
a pretty vulgar analogy. It just says
that it's a minimization process.
Um the second however is where I have
more of a problem. It says
uh okay I guess I'll read this whole
paragraph. Uh the second point of
connection between Hamiltonian physics
and active inference arises from a more
direct association between Hamiltonian
and probability measures. Uh this
appears to just be uh more or less um
assumed. Uh the the idea here is to
associate the conserved Hamiltonian with
the energy of the system which of course
you know it you the Hamiltonian usually
is the the energy of the system at least
with what you would deal with. Uh but
then
it oh wait yeah so here here's the
problem. It says that remember that
quantities here referred to of energies
have had the form of negative log
probability. The only reason you're
allowed to do that is because of because
it's the Boltzman distribution, right?
You use the Boltzman distribution to to
to have that equation. Um this
reflects energy. This reflects an
interpretation of energy is simply a
measurement of improbability. That is
simply not what energy is. energy is
simply the conserved quantity that you
get because
um
because the laws of physics are
symmetric under time translation, right?
And then uh and then it says on this
view conservation of energy and
probability are equivalent laws. And I
have a problem with that too because
um the I the idea that conservation of
energy and conservation of probability
are different actually underly the
construction of the Boltzman
distribution. So uh
if uh oh I should by say by the way this
is on page 55.
Um the yeah these are great points and
questions. I I But you let me finish
because the really important point is
that it says that uh conservation of
energy and probability are the same. But
that probably can't be the case because
if it was then you wouldn't have the
Boltzman distribution because the
Boltzman distribution is constructed by
assuming that those are two different
conservations that you have. If you
don't have the Boltzman distribution
then you also don't have the association
between energies and negative log
probabilities.
So, uh, yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Great point.
Write it down. Just with you've
highlighted the part that you've taken a
clear perspective on. Write it down.
Post it in Discord andor Zenoto. Let's
ask those who can evaluate it in a more
methodical way. But great points.
Okay, if that's uh if if this topic is
discussed, I would like to uh uh
question a different figure in the book
in the
chapter. So
if if this is discussed okay then my pro
u what I would like to get more
intuition on is figure 3.2 two which
essentially states that internal
uh dynamics will uh go will do the thing
uh will not mimic external dynamics but
I don't understand how how to interpret
this picture and how to like get some
real life examples about how how I
should really interpret that and 3.2
uh figure
okay just to to lead into 3.2 do. So
first Nacho asked action states refer to
the possible actions the system I do
almost. So the possible actions that are
available are the
affordances. So that's like the the the
the dictionary of words that are
possibly playable. The action state in a
given moment or the active state is the
actual selected action in that moment.
So possible actions would be like I
could turn the wheel left, right or
straight and then the action state for
the markoff blanket of the car would be
the wheel is turning to the
left. So that's what it gets interfaced.
So yeah, so what gets interfaced to the
environment is the selected single
action whether it's from a discrete or
from a continuous space but from the
internal side the deck of cards. Okay.
So we're working with this topological
partitioning of the agent environment
scenario. Blanket states intermediate
between internal and external states.
It's called the particular partition as
sort of a little pun because it's this
one particular way to partition it. It's
not saying this is the only way to
partition it. It's saying this is a
particular way to partition action and
perception and there's other ways which
can be proposed and have been proposed
also particular carries this connotation
of like carving out a particle. So if we
think about brownie in motion and sort
of the example of looking at a dust
particle vibrating in the microscope in
the water from like thermal vibration
um that's a particle on a backdrop and
so this partition carves out the
particle which is like the agents or the
thing from that which is not the thing.
Okay.
Now, how how does that look
probabilistically? Okay, so we have
three different
[Music]
um variables that are going to be looked
at here. This
one I always think for this uh diagram,
the Girdleerbach book cover. Okay, so we
have one object and then it's going to
be projected in three different
dimensions onto two
dimensions. So we have X which is like X
marks a spot latent or hidden or
external state. So that's like the true
temperature in the room. Then there's mu
which is the internal states like mu for
mind b for
blanket vertical line means conditioned
upon. So that's what these um different
two-dimensional
projections at any given moment you have
a value for external blanket and
internal. So any given moment in the
simulation is a point in a
three-dimensional joint
distribution. Now we're going to
condition upon some variables and look
at the remaining
um scatter in the two dimensions. So
here is internal
states with respect to with linear
regression on blanket
states. So this is like this
relationship here is external
states conditioned on blanket states. So
now these two it it it these both are
sort of like directly connected because
external states are connected to the
blanket. They have an actual direct
causal edge. Internal states are
connected to the blanket. They have a
direct causal edge. So these two the
fact that there's like a statistically
significant regression or a mutual
information is kind of given by the
definition of direct causality.
But here we see that there's actually
also a probabilistic relationship albeit
a little bit more scattered because it's
more mediated between internal and
external states even though they don't
directly connect
causally. What this crosshairs
represents is that
here is x and note that the scale like
just look at this you know here's the
scale is -105 but it's just heristic but
here it's a little different here we
have x is at
-6 and the internal state is at
48. So this
curve is
like this hump like imagine if this were
scattered if these points were
importance
sampling based upon the elevation of a
landscape. That's sort of the optimistic
view. We're sampling more from the
higher probability areas like those are
the data points we selected from the
experiment. or in flip that picture. Now
the lower higher probability things have
a lower
energy. And so then we're thinking about
like it's a valley and we're sampling
the location of a ball in the valley and
it is going to be found more in the
bottom of the valley. But in either
case, if you take a cross-section right
here, you'll get this distribution.
And so what this distribution represents
is the belief distribution about
external states the
expectation of internal
states conditioned on the blanket. So
this is kind of showing how you have a
causal edge between external and
blanket, causal edge between blanket and
internal and mediated through that chain
of causality. You can get mutual
information between external and
internal states. And then you could have
a situation where like the internal
states are about temperature. External
states are temperature and you have a
you know one one or a positive or simple
linear correlation. Or you could have a
more complex mutual information setting
where there still is information of the
internal states on the external states
but it's not like just trying to track
it like a stock
price and say I I see that because you
speak of this mutual information and
that manifests itself in these trends.
Um but they also speak about it
mimicking the causal structure of the
world like
internally. Um is that also what they
claim here about know the internal
states trying mimicking the causal
structure of the external world or is
that interpretation not justified here?
So it's not required. For example,
common is external state will be a
temperature value that's continuous. And
then the homeostat like the agent or the
thermometer on the wall is just three
discrete states like low, medium or
high. Or it could have five like too
low, lower boundary just right, upper
boundary too high. So theru the
structure of the agent's internal
generative model that distribution or it
could be totally nonsensical like the
temperatures from the outside could be a
Gaussian distribution and the agent
could be trying to do the best
variational inference they could on a
totally different variational
family. So it in the general case it
doesn't have
to have the same
structure. So this comes up a lot in
modeling because and why it's so
important and chapter six goes into
these kinds of points is like what is
the point of the model because for
example if you have an agent who knows
the consequences of its actions like it
knows that when it does action up it's
going to move up in the world then it is
going to do inference on where to move
but you've kind of sidestepped this
question of how it comes to learn what
those affordances
or the possibility of those affordants
changing their consequence. Or if you
have an agent that already knows that
it's locked into
temperature, then you've kind of given
it a causal head start or structural
head start where it's like in the right
ballpark. Or another example in the
T-mise that comes back in chapter 7, the
rat already knows that there's two
contexts that there's like two
signs that either signal the food is
probably on left or the food is probably
on the right. So chapter 7 is like
saying we've already trained this rat to
understand the teammate's game and to to
undergo this seiosis of learning that
the sign at the bottom represents the
probability of reward being on either of
the two arms of the teammates. So that
model doesn't address how do rats learn
about how food is on one side of a
teammates or not.
So I think I understand. So for me uh
so for example I am um a system and I
have an internal temperature and even
though my internal temperature doesn't
directly influence the external
environment we do see that my internal
temperature does is synchronized with
the external temperature and that's like
then what like this synchronization but
also V2 points that we get these kind of
synchronizations with this particular
partition also motivated
almost I might say the slightly simpler
case is is the internal belief about
outside temperature and then the outside
temperature. You could also have a model
where there's an outside temperature and
then there's a system with an internal
temperature and it's doing its own
temperature homeostasis that
way. It's like th those are those are
structurally different
models. So, you know, all models are
incomplete slash wrong, some are useful.
That's kind of the whole point is
there's a variety of models and
depending on what you're trying to
reduce your uncertainty about or
frame various combinations. And in
practice, we build like kind of
portfolios of models and look at
similarities and differences in
different attributes about them. Not
just try to build one and just say,
"Okay, this was like the model." Uh John
uh hello. So I have some questions that
are related to each other about priors
and
preferences. Uh so I I guess the first
one is um when you talk about priors
typically the posterior is used as like
the prior for the next phase of
inference. So, does the uh do the
preferences change a as you do
successive sequences of
inference? Great question. First,
absolutely correct. like the prior if
people just say just that alone usually
they're talking about the prior on the
latent state d on s but technically
every variable has a prior then the
posterior the post update value becomes
like the prior for the next moment
that's the basian experience
about preferences you can have a model
with preference updating you can have a
model with preference learning
but you don't have do. So you can have a
preference that updates in a prior
posterior basian fashion or you can just
have a fixed preference variable which
is corresponding to like an infinite
precision fixed preference distribution.
Okay. So, so the second thing is I I
think I could like imagine a situation
in which the prior is different from a
preference. Like I could imagine a child
who might have a different prior uh to
meeting lions. A a different prior
probability than a different than uh
their preference in the sense that uh
the probability might be higher than the
preference. Uh and I don't see how how
those would be the same in that case.
Yeah. So it's like for example like I
would really love to win this
lotto but I'm also reconciling that with
I have a low belief that it's likely you
know it's not likely to happen. Is that
kind of the situation you're talking
about? Uh yeah just you know if it's a
prior. So um you know you could clearly
get around this by saying it's not
really a prior in some situations. So,
but you know the thing the thing about
the child and the lions is that it's a
real prior because the child hasn't met
a lion
before. Yeah. So, let's just say we have
preference
on seeing lion not seeing
lion. And this variable is going to look
like like this. We're just taking that
that as a binary observation. I'm going
to say one and
100. Okay.
Massive preference to not see a lion.
That's the the preference distribution
is over observables. Then latent state,
you know, latent state, hidden state,
external state, all the same
thing. prior on latent state and this is
context with
lion context no
lion and that variable the child is
going to say I think it's 80% likely
that lions are
around 20% likely and then the a matrix
would be a 2x two let's just say that it
looks like
rows and columns are these two. So here
with lion always maps to seeing a
lion. No lion always maps to no seeing
line. And this is the identity matrix.
If this were all 0.5s it would be the
whole situation would be grayed out. or
if it were like 0.9 and 0.1 it would
just be like kind of a messy or slightly
ambiguous
observation. So even within a single
layer model so not appealing to like
hierarchical like beliefs on beliefs and
things like that we already get the
exact kind of behavior you're talking
about where it's possible for there to
be a preference for something to happen
and a very different belief about how
likely it is to happen. But that's even
just within a very simple single layer
model. If you want to talk about like
kind of, you know, more sophisticated
things, those can be built out from
there. But it's actually expressive
enough to hold that at the base too.
So So you say that the uh the connection
between prior and preferences isn't um
isn't iron.
Priors on what?
Um, well, we could use the lions, right?
Right. These are separate variables. So,
they're up to the modeler or the
situation of interest. Okay. But I think
it says uh I don't Hold on. I have to I
have to go find the text. I'm
think I think I'm arguing with Hold
on. I mean, don't hold on. I I I'll be
back in a few
minutes. Yeah. I'm also here. I'm going
to bring in this is kind of a a
very very classic
slide. This is from live stream 37. the
paper
um it's called free energy a user's
guide. They talk about how the same
distribution can play a a sort of
linguistic
onlogical role as the probability of
something
occurring. That's sort of the naked
statistical
sense, the
preference as well as the fitness in the
historical tally setting. So if we think
about this in temperature, it's like
there's my body temperature throughout
the day. It's like Gaussian around
37. So that's just the probability
distribution. But that also can be
reflected as like the constraints or the
preference
distribution assuming that's like
homeostatic and
healthy. And then similarly that can be
seen in the in the sort of population
scale as being like adaptive to
fitness because if there was some other
distribution that had higher fitness
then that statistical phenotype would
have come to predominate in the
environment. So is it because of fitness
that you the child doesn't grow to not
expect lions?
Yeah, this is a great question.
So then this is this is this is um the
kind of work that that um with Bristen
and others I've focused on in the last
several years too. You know where do
those priors come from? Well so what I'm
really asking is what's the exact
difference between priors and
preferences
like in the general case? Well, no, an
active inference because it seems like
they're the claim is that they're pretty
much the same. It seems to say that in
the textbook.
Which part does are you looking at in
the textbook? I I don't know. I have to
I have to look for it, but it seems to
say it in chapter three and in other
chapters. Yeah. Like the general case is
very general.
If you look at a specific model or if
you make a specific model then the
difference between this and that will
just become so plainly deflationarily
clear. It's like I
mean are subway map are subways drawn
thicker or thinner than highways on the
map in general? It's like well in
general no because you could do you
could have a map with or without subways
or you could draw them any way you want.
But then you look at a specific map, you
go, "Okay, it's
thinner." So it's like some of these
things in the general
case, not like it's the closure of the
discussion, but in the general case, you
go, "Yeah, you could do it one way or
you could do it another way because it's
like the general toolkit." You know, how
many wheels does a wheeled object have
in the general case? 1 2 3 4 5. How many
wheels does this car have? Oh, four. Oh,
it has three. Okay.
But that's like the literal difference
between the general case and the
framework and the toolkit and the
possibilities and the modeler degrees of
freedom and the specific generative
models that you build, which is to say
the specific or the particular joint
distributions defining the generative
model.
Okay, another question from not
show. In this sense, active inference
defends a form of modal
representationalism similar to Fodor's
idea, but modal, not just digital. Do
you want to like add a little more
context, Nacho, or does anyone have any
thoughts on this?
Certainly this question of
representation has come up like just
looking at the
titles from streams and papers.
questions about representation
in
semantics. How do signs and signifiers
and represent uh come to represent and
be understood to represent and you know
reference questions like that?
this um paper of Matt
Sims. This one is kind of this one's
kind
of a classic to this earlier point where
it's like there's the general setting
where it's like you know wheeled objects
could have any number of wheels and then
there's the specific settings. What Sims
does in this paper is says okay on four
different ways of thinking about the
concept of representation organizational
representation structural content and
functional
representation. There's a
representationalist and a non or
anti-representationalist
view. And then the paper
is what does it mean about our own
understandings in where we come
down on representationalism and not on
these columns.
Representationalism means that our
experience is uh one big representation
of the outside world or like it's how I
see this list that our experience is a
experience explanation of our sens
sensory
input is that what representation
doesn't
mean you're you're in the ballpark like
each of these four I just don't really
remember the details. Each of those four
different columns take a different view
on what representation is.
Okay.
But that's a great paper to look at. Oh
yeah, I'm learn. Yeah.
like does something represent does cup
represent that
cup
if if it um propositionally invokes the
cup but I don't actionably know what to
do what about the other setting where I
have no propositional understanding of
it but I go to grab that cup when
somebody says
cup and so each of those or what you
know and so And it relates to this
earlier discussion on temperature. Like
what does it mean for the agent to have
a representation of temperature of the
outside temperature? Does that mean that
they have a variable that needs to have
mutual information and monotonically
track it? But what if it's a terrible
representation? You know, is a bad
representation still a
representation? What if it's actionable
but has a very different
semantics? John
Uh okay, I found what I'm was
complaining about in the textbook. So it
says uh let me make sure this is the
right. Yeah, it says it unites. So in
contrast in active inference, behavior
is the result of inference and
optimization is and its optimization is
a function of beliefs. This formulation
unites notions of prior belief and
preference as discussed above using the
notion of expected free energy. And then
it says something I think about the uh
optimistic view. Yeah, I'm sure there's
a ton of ways to read this, but it
unites them like if you unite flour and
water to make dough. So here there's the
uniting of these two different variables
into a joint distribution. So it's not
saying that they are pointing to the
same variable. It's saying we're
uniting two different kinds of things,
prior beliefs and preferences. You know,
D on S for example, and C. uniting
different variables in a joint
distribution in order to get to this
unified type of model or map for
sensemaking and action selection
systems. Okay, but it says it's endowing
the agent with an implicit prior belief
that it will realize its preferences. So
that's that's like saying it endows the
child with an implicit prior belief that
it will uh realize not seeing any lions.
Using the notion of expected free energy
amounts to endowing the agent. So if we
don't have an action selector, we just
have an a like a rock that's not
engaging in counterfactual policy
inference. It's not saying the EF is
like expected in the pragmatic uh
expected pragmatic and epistemic value
equation 2.6 in the textbook. So if it
is engaging in this energybased
method with an expected free energy
functional such that pragmatic value
which is to say alignment with
preferences are seen as more likely
that's why we sample from them. Okay. So
when you say energy I just have to
clarify because it says in the textbook
that energy is seen simply as a measure
of improbability. Is that how you're
using energy? Yeah exactly. So here
there's there's a direct we have the
policy prior pi then expected free
energy operates on the policy prior and
it updates it according to pragmatic and
epistemic value. So let's just leave
epistemic value off to the side um for a
second. So here's figure
2.6. So here's expected free energy on
policy. We have a vector of policies.
Let's just say we could go up, down,
left, right. our policy prior. They're
all even. Or you could have a habit, but
they're all even. Then we're going to
update
that probability distribution over
action according to the epistemic and
the pragmatic value of those actions.
So in that situation where we are
explicitly upweing the probability of
selecting actions that fulfill our
preferences then we have endowed the
agent with a prior belief that it will
realize those
preferences. If you said, "I'm going to
make a counter
ef it seems also in other chapters such
as chapter 2 that it talks about uh
preferences being defined by priors."
And I'm just not sure that that can be
made to work in all situations.
Yeah. Find that situation and then
you've made an advance in FEP. Well,
well, it's the lion thing with the
children, right? Cuz um what does the
prior of the the children with the lions
have to do with their preferences?
Okay. So again, we're in a thought
thought kind of counterfactual where the
only observation is whether we see a
lion or not. And then the latent state
is whether we're in a context with lions
or not. And so it's like what what is
the
aboutness of what is the relationship
between the preference for seeing it or
not and the belief about whether they
are out there or not? Well, that's sort
of my question. Yeah. What is it that
connects the dots? Lions. Children in
situations with or without lions
connects the
dots. It's like, I made this map. What
is it that connects all of these
representations on the map? It's like
the
territory. But if it's a fantastical
everchanging
territory, don't expect the map to have
too much
coherence. But if you pick a fixed
scenario for what is the actual process
that you're modeling, then you'll find
you can make many coherent
maps with not much ado.
So, so there's a difference between the
prior and the preference in this
example, right? Like look look at the
the array is there. Yeah. The slight
ambiguity is sometimes when people just
say a prior they mean a a prior on the
latent state like a prior on S D on S.
Like if we look at the
figures sometimes this one right here
three or D is called the
prior. In a more general basian updating
context every variable has a prior.
Now, some of them are learnable or not.
First question about whether the
preferences update when the priors
update. It it could you can do
preference learning or not. Well, I I I
just I I just don't understand exactly
what the connection between the priors
and preferences is supposed to be
because in the lion example, they seem
separated. Um here's the the context. Is
there are we in the lion context or not?
Here's observations about lion or
not. Preferences have the same form as a
distribution over
observations. The reason why models
always have almost always have updating
of beliefs on latent states is because
that's where actions
intervene. So if there was no updating
of latent
states, there would be no purpose in
intervening. So action selection would
be this moot kind of epifenomenal
question. So for the agent to believe it
has agency, which may not be the case in
the simulation as you set it up, it
could believe that it's changing the
stock market just by like switching
channels on the TV. So it doesn't need
to have a veritical
representation, but that's that whole
representation question. If you have a
representation that's nonveritical, is
it a representation at all?
And the general case
is read the Mad Sims paper, see what you
think about that and where you put
yourself. But in the particular case of
a given
model, you you resolve that just by
writing out the distribution you're
talking about. Are you talking about a
person regulating their temperature and
their air conditioner and the heater
work or are you talking about a
situation where the air conditioner and
the heater are not plugged in, but they
still believe that they are. But those
are modeling different
scenarios. But even just right there,
that's why the general case doesn't come
down on such an opinionated way because
you could just think of those situations
right off the bat where the agent does
or doesn't have causal
efficacy. So if the agent is the causal
efficacy the thing that tells you
whether the priors are the same as the
preferences or not?
Okay, this variable priors on latent
states is not preferences is never the
same as the preferences. Okay, it can be
related to the same situation. I can
have a preference on body temperature
like observations, interceptive
temperature observations and prior
belief on temperature in the room.
They're separate
variables. So,
I feel like the textbook argues in
several places that they're the same.
Um,
the textbook is just pixels. Your
perception of it is what you're
experiencing.
Uh, okay. I I'll look through it and
I'll probably send you some quotes
because I feel like this is a thing that
it says and it see it seems like a thing
that you're saying half the time. Uh,
but
yeah, great. Absolutely. Not saying
I'm correct, not saying the textbook is
fully correct, but it's recorded and
it's
written. So, pull out the specific parts
and then that's the conversation. Well,
I think it's in chapter 2. So, I found
this one part um uh but I think it goes
on. So, yeah, it says that it says that
the agent will have an implicit prior
belief that it will realize its
preferences.
So does the does the child have an
implicit prior belief that it will
realize it's it's okay using the notion
of expected free energy amounts to
endowing the agent. So okay now we're
going to go back to the child. Now the
child the policy okay we have run
towards lion forest is option one and
then run away from lion forest. So now
we're bringing action into the picture.
Okay, if it just Okay, so now its
preference is not to see
lions. So now let's just say that it's
its
habit policy
prior. Again, this is like
why we we use the
ontology like this because it's not in
this infinite set of words like there's
a policy prior it let's just say it's
0.5 then it's going to do expected free
energy calculation or we're going to
model it as if it's doing expected free
energy
calculation the policy and and we're
we're going to discount
epistemic value. Okay, so we're just
looking at this
setting with just pragmatic value. Maybe
curiosity makes it go there, right?
That's that's the second question, but
just on the pragmatic preference
satisficing elements. Okay, which one of
these policies is going to have higher
pragmatic value? Well, running towards
the lion forest makes me believe that
we're going to be in a state where there
is lion, which makes me believe we're
going to see a lion. Running away from
the lion forest makes me believe that
I'll transition into a state where
there's no lion, which is more apt to
have the not seeing of a lion. So, this
one is going to have higher pragmatic
value. Yeah, but it won't have enough
value to change that 82 distribution
into that one.
Like really, you should look at the
specifics of models because you could
have it so that it's so overpowering
that it updates from 991 to 199. That's
the whole situation with the
frog is here. It's 10 10% it's a
frog and then after it goes to
0.9. So that is belief weighted updating
which is where if you didn't pay
attention to the observation it has no
impact. You carry your prior forward. If
you had full attention to the
observation you would say okay well now
it's 100% it's a frog or it's 99% it's a
a a
frog. And then everything in between is
the the gradation of attention and
that's attention weighted basian belief
updating that just gets down to the
quantitative detail here. I'm just
laying out the
structure of it.
Okay. So, so is the the short answer
that the prior is different from the
preferences and that these are just
different numbers,
right? The short answer is the prior is
different than the preferences. They're
two prior on latent states is over here.
Three preferences comes into play over
here. We can look at 7 uh
three. D is a prior on latent states. C
is a probability distribution on
observations. They don't even have the
same structure. They're two separate
variables. They come together. They're
united in this model where if you use
expected free energy, it implicitly
endows the agent with this belief just
focusing on the pragmatic value that it
is taking actions that make its
preferences more likely to be
realized. Secondary things like how does
epistemic value modify that picture? How
well does it modify um how how well does
it achieve its preferences? you know,
how how agentic is it? The there's all
these secondary questions, but just to
the primaascia and all of the quotes
that you've raised, I hope that makes it
kind of
clear and it becomes clear when you
actually write out a specific
example because the general case
delightfully doesn't resolve
it.
Anyone who hasn't
um raised a question or said anything
want to just like add any
pieces some interesting part on three or
another figure or quote
Hey, Daniel. Uh, this is Jerry. not uh
not necessarily specifically related to
that, but I did have a question um kind
of cuz you brought up that u that
article about like Evo DVO. Is there
anything tying this um this framework to
more of an evolutionary like predatory
prey type of view of things in terms of
human behavior that comes into play like
as to how we you know search for
patterns and consume patterns if you
will out there as you were referring to
like pixels but then we make meaning of
it.
Yeah. Few few thoughts there. So one
interesting connection with a predator
prey that will come up
[Music]
in chapter 8 in the continuous time
generative model is actually the way
that lock goer
models are used to to model winnerless
competitions. Mhm. So here's like the
the true classical ecological here's a
threepart
ecosystem where you know and there's
there's parameterizations that lead to
collapse of populations etc. But this is
just one setting where you have these
three cyclic um you know these model and
then also here's those those same the
same GEB book cover here's this
three-dimensional phase space being
projected onto
two 2D phase spaces just like we saw
with internal blanket external but here
with yeah um
so that has been used in SPM and
neuroiming to model relations among
activity in brain
regions with like certain brain regions
that have positive edges or negative
edges. But even when there's a positive
edge, it might lead to increased
activity and another positive edge and a
negative edge. So like the plus plus
minus triad leads to dampening feedback
with a lag.
So it's been used extensively in dynamic
causal modeling and continuous time
modeling. Now more to the human side.
Maybe look at the epistemic communities.
Yeah, I've seen that one before with
Mao. Yeah, cool. So that's kind of like
that. Um I don't
know if anyone has done like lock
voltera too much further on some
specific um but but you know like right
that those are the seeds of pursuing
that inquiry you know okay would you be
measuring this could be you know the
sentiment score in three different
cryptocurrency chains or this could be
you know three politicians and their
polling numbers or it sentiment of this
or that and then it's like these are
kind of the
macroscopic dynamic causal
model that this is basically giving the
toolkit
around. Got it. Yeah, that's where my
head was going because I work in
marketing and communications and like
you know we've got the purchase funnel
which is just a bunch of madeup stuff.
But I was trying to think of it in terms
of more of that um that predator prey
model if you would and like getting some
uh bringing some computation in around
like how those steps are for a predator
to go and hunt and consume if you would
because I think there's some connection
there in human behavior that we haven't
quite made computational in my world. We
tend to do it more like it's folk
wisdom. But I think there's parallels
and I think it would explain a lot. But
it's good to know I'm at least pointed
in the right direction. I did find one
computational model of uh predator
behavior that I think was kind of
interesting, but I was just curious from
your perspective if there was anything
else. But it looks like I'm at least in
the right
ballpark. Yeah. Yeah. like predatory
lending or things like I mean the just
where is that qualitative
metaphor coarse graining some more
actionable specific quantitative models
that could be I think where it's
interesting like you said it's it's it's
a different levels right like I think
consumers it's funny we call them that
right but like consumers um they are
hunting if you will for something that
would effectively
um make them feel better. But to your
point as well, corporations like
basically I think put out like a lure,
if you will, like they're they're
affordances they're putting out there to
be picked up like you know, some in a
more symbiotic way, some in a more
parasitic way. So, I think there's
definitely some uh
biological uh research that we could
bring in to like give that a better
metaphor.
Yeah. And these kind of like nomadic
metaphors like where are we looking more
at message passing and belief sharing
and updating in a multi-agentic
model? Where are we looking more at
macroscopic macroeconomic summary
fluctuations? And then you know where do
you want a fusion model where there's
like a macroscopic lending rate
that's like the temperature and the
niche and then there's specific offers
and then there's like agent level
cognitive patterns you know act now to
lock in this
rate and then what kinds of cognitive
structures have what kinds of responses
and updating of their habits.
Yeah. Yeah. And um I think it's a good
call out on that locker because I'd seen
that before and I think it's tied into
some economic models if I'm not
mistaken. So
um it that's an interesting place for me
to dig in a little bit more. So thank
you for
that. Yeah. I've I've also seen some
like like ecology of fear. Oh, okay.
This is kind of an other than being kind
of a intense sounding concept, but it's
just like predators and prey, whatever,
however you want to think of it, food
chain, food ladder, food web, you know,
trophic, they're cognitive systems.
So their
biosemiosis and their cognitive
processes, it's it's not just about like
the last mile of the cheetah chasing the
gazelle. They're both engaging in these
cognitive evolutionary strategies where
over
success might reduce population fitness.
And those are kind of higher order
evolutionary consequences that
intergenerational frameworks could start
to to model
because what if you what if what if
local depopulation of
deer isn't high fitness for populations
of carnivores?
Mhm.
But but then at the single agent level
it's like well optimal foraging says you
should just be like on this killing
rampage.
Right. Right. And I think there there's
definitely some parallels there in the
work that I do. And um the um the active
inference communities work that you
pulled up is also very interesting
because I think it gets to from our
standpoint like the messaging that we're
putting out for people to consume. Share
voice is something we talk about a lot
which would you know inform those
priors, right? um and and update the you
know update people's beliefs based on
what they're what they are seeing the
most of and that's what we see in in our
work and so that's what I'm trying to
kind of noodle on is how do I you know
merge that from a communication
standpoint um and use some of these I
think easier to understand evolutionary
terms for people
Yeah.
Yeah. But the economy of advertising
advertising where um is the arbit info
arbitrage among other things between how
do we spend to update
beliefs? Beliefs about what? That's the
representation question. Beliefs for
whom? Like what other beliefs are
tethered or already preassociated with
it? Like advertising is cognitive,
economics is cognitive. That's like the
cognitive term in everything. And then
there's the pragmatic turn in the
cognitive sciences which is enacted
extended you pragmatic all those
features and then where all those are
sort of
swirling is is the space of
actionoriented cognitive modeling.
Right. Right. Yeah. totally makes sense.
There's really some interesting work in
my field around uh aggregate attention
because there we're getting more to the
space where we can not just measure
viewability but actual attention paid to
messages and that that aggregate amount
across channels like really is
predictive of how belief changes about
the organization that is presenting it
and the sales that they then eventually
have. They seem very fixed, but we do
know that that's a a big thing. Yeah,
the attention economy stuff for sure.
Um is definitely something that plays
into that.
Cool.
Yep. And then just walking these
domains along the road of applicability
and rigor from like intuitive,
qualitative,
metaphorical on but then there's so many
terminal branches. There's so many
generative models that could be made. So
then that's the sort of forwards
backwards process in feedback with
domain experts and all of this. You know
what are the observables? What are the
latent states we should be making? What
are the preferences? What are the priors
on what that we're modeling? What would
be a question we'd want a computational
model to address? And that's the kind of
chapter six questions.
Yep. Cool. Yeah, thank you for that. I
do have to to jump, but that was super
helpful and gave me a few more things to
chew on.
Fun. Um, okay. Well, so next week if
people want to join at this same
time we'll be
discussing chapter 8 which we just
peaked at
here. Otherwise in two weeks at this
time
um we will be having our first
discussion on chapter
4 which is where we actually get
introduced to the active inference
generative
model.
So thank you all. See you next
time. Bye.